Today’s דף daf is פ"ח, Pech-Chet, 88. We pick up on the
bottom of פ"ז עמוד ב Pez-Zayin Amud Bet after having gone through—we're
now on a new topic. The new topic is the right of
a worker to eat as he's doing the work,
and the basic principle of the משנה Mishna is basically the פסוק
pasuk in תורה Torah is כי תבוא בקמת רעך וקטפת מלילות בידך
וחרמש לא תניף על קמת רעך, Ki tavo bekamat re'echa vekatafta melilot
beyadecha vechermesh lo tanif al kamat re'echa, when you go into your
friend's standing grain, you can take some of the kernels in your
hand by your hand, but don't use a scythe. And similarly, it
says when you go into the vineyard, you can take, put some
of the grapes, eat them till you're filled, but don't put them
into your vessel. It's not explicit in the פסוקים psukim that we're
talking about a worker, but חז"ל Chazal understand that we're talking about
a worker, and they yesterday we saw the דרשות drashot that they
learn to teach us that it applies to all types of growing
produce. It's not limited to those two. That it is at the
time of גמר מלאכה Gmar Melacha when—this phrase of גמר מלאכה Gmar
Melacha is different than the one we'll introduce in a minute, but
this basically means when the stuff is being harvested, cut from the
ground. So that's the moment that it applies.
And if it grows from the ground and גמר מלאכה, Gmar Melacha,
a worker in any type of thing, not limited to those two,
can basically eat as he is working. And then there's another discussion
about dealing with stuff that's already been picked from the ground, which
we will get to. So let's take a look at the bottom,
yes.
Just like trees, stuff that grows from the ground? Yep. So if
you pick the fruit, you're harvesting fruit?
Exactly. All right. Now the גמרא Gemara says bottom of כ"ז עמוד
ב, Kaf-Zayin Amud Bet,
one, two, three, six lines before it gets
wide, yes, six lines, והשתא דנפקא לן מחרמש ומקמה למה לי. Vahashta
denafka lan michermesh umikama lama li. Now that we've learned out it
applies to all types of growing things from the word חרמש, chermesh,
the scythe, which is anything that could be cut by a scythe,
and קמה, kama, anything that's growing and standing, so כי תבוא בכרם
רעך למה לי? Ki tavo becherem re'echa lama li? Why do I
need the verse about the vineyard? Because just give me the one
verse about the wheat and let me extrapolate from it. Why do
I also need the verse about the vineyard? So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רבא להלכותיו, Amar Rava lehilchotav, in order to—because there are
very specific parameters of this הלכה halacha that a worker can eat,
and many of those parameters we learn out from the פסוקים psukim
about the vineyard. כדתניא Kidetanya like we taught in
a ברייתא: braita: כי תבוא בכרם רעך ואכלת ענבים
כנפשך שבעך ואל כליך לא תתן. Ki tavo becherem re'echa veachalta anavim
kenafshecha sov'echa ve'el kelyecha lo titen. When you come into your friend's
vineyard, you shall eat grapes to your fill, but do not put
it into your vessel. So now we're going to דרש darshan each
part of that פסוק. pasuk. Okay. כי
תבוא, Ki tavo, נאמר כאן ביאה ונאמר להלן לא תבוא עליו השמש,
Nemar kan bi'ah venemar lehalan lo tavo alav hashemesh, which is another
part of the worker's right—you know, I should—it's funny I shouldn't call
it worker's rights, because that's a very Western thing to talk about
rights. But
anyway—so, but obligation to the workers, right, is to not postpone their
payment of their fees of their pay. So לא תבוא עליו השמש,
lo tavo alav hashemesh, the sun cannot set. So נאמר כאן ביאה
ונאמר להלן ביאה, nemar kan bi'ah venemar lehalan bi'ah, מה להלן בפועל
הכתוב
מדבר אף כאן בפועל הכתוב מדבר. mah lehalan bepo'el hakatuv medaber af
kan bepo'el hakatuv medaber. So first of all, that tells us that
we're talking about a פועל, po'el, a worker, not that you're just
cutting through somebody's vineyard. Okay? It's specifically somebody who is hired as
a פועל, po'el, a worker, to be harvesting the grapes.
Now, בכרם רעך, Becherem re'echa, your friend's vineyard, ולא בכרם גוי. velo
becherem Goy. Now the word here is not כותי, Kuti, the word
here is גוי. Goy. Okay?
Not in the vineyard of a non-Jew. In the vineyard of a
non-Jew, you are—you do not have these restrictions. So what does that
mean?
I mean—eat more.
Right, meaning you take more, meaning you could have said, oh, you're
not allowed to if you're working for a non-Jew. Which is—it's funny
because the פסוק pasuk is coming to allow you to do it,
but actually the פסוק pasuk here is actually saying like, no, there
are none of these like restrictions. Like you're working for a non-Jew
and you can go ahead and you can even take some for
later or do it even שלא בשעת גמר מלאכה. shelo bish'at Gmar
Melacha. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, הניחא למאן
דאמר גזל גוי אסור. Ha nicha leman d'amar gezel goy asur. That's
good if you say normally it's forbidden to steal from a non-Jew.
So then this has to tell you, this isn't a problem of
stealing, this is when you're working for a non-Jew you have more
latitude. You can store—you can take and put it away for later.
Okay?
היינו דאיצטריך למישרי פועל. Haynu deitztarich lemishre po'el. That's to give special
allowance to a פועל. po'el. אלא למאן דאמר גזל גוי מותר. Ela
leman d'amar gezel goy mutar. But if it's generally permissible to steal
from a non-Jew, השתא גזילה מותר פועל מבעיא? hashta gezeila mutar po'el
mibaya? So if there's no prohibition of stealing, why, of course, you
don't need to allow more latitude here for a worker? So obviously
deeply disturbing גמרא, Gemara, although—which
part is more disturbing than the other part?
Well, to say that there are somewhat different parameters is not so
disturbing. I mean, it depends what the גוי Goy thinks, you know.
But anyway, it doesn't matter, it doesn't matter. Obviously the idea that
גזל גוי gezel Goy could be מותר—as mutar we saw in בבא
קמא—and Bava Kama here the גמרא Gemara is seeing that as almost
an equivalent option, right, and, you know, and seems to have no
compunctions if it's מותר. mutar. It's מותר *mutar*, you don't need any
special allowance. Anyway, we'll get, I'll read you תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* in
a minute. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so פרה וסוס *parah
vesus*, מוקמינן לה *mokminan lah*, so what do you need the רישא
*reisha* to tell me? מוקמינן לה בכרם רעך ולא של הקדש *mokminan
lah bekarem re'acha velo shel hekdesh*. If you're working for הקדש *hekdesh*,
then it is the opposite thing. It's not that you have the
restrictions when it's, when
one way of saying if it's a יהודי *Yehudi* you have the
restrictions, if it's a גוי *goy* you don't have restrictions. Here's the
opposite. If it's a יהודי *Yehudi* you have the allowance to take
the grapes or the whatever the food is, but if you're working
in הקדש *hekdesh*, you don't have that allowance. Now of course that's
a little funny because the stuff is הקדש *hekdesh* anyway and were
you to eat it forget גזל *gezel* it would be מעילה *me'ilah*.
So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says well, but the same way the תורה
Torah *Torah* is sort of telling you it's not גזל *gezel* when
you eat the grapes of your friend if you're working, maybe the
תורה Torah *Torah* would have waived the מעילה *me'ilah* concerns as well.
Now that makes some degree of sense if you think that מעילה
*me'ilah* is fundamentally a form of גזילה *gezeilah*, that fundamentally מעילה *me'ilah*
is taking something away from הקדש *hekdesh* to belong to הקדש *hekdesh*.
But if מעילה *me'ilah* is some type of a sense of impinging
on the קדושה *kedushah*, the status of it, you know, it doesn't
really make that much sense what the הוה אמינא hava amina *hava
amina* would have been. It's also possible to contemplate a case although
this is rare that something could be owned by הקדש *hekdesh* but
not actually have קדושה *kedushah*. So if you could imagine, רמב"ן *Ramban*
discusses some scenarios like that. Like he says, let's say something falls
into הקדש *hekdesh*'s field, okay, so it's קדוש *kadosh* but not because
you verbally, because they own it, because it's like קנין חצר chatzer.
*kinyan chatzer*, but since nobody verbally sanctified it maybe it wouldn't have
קדושה *kedushah*. אבידה *avedah*, not anything, אבידה *avedah* falls in הקדש *hekdesh*'s
field. Anyway, but it's hard to find that scenario. Yes.
We have the example where they had they stones that they wanted
people to be able to rest on and they didn't want to
make them הקדש *hekdesh* and so...
right, that's true, somebody was giving something to הקדש *hekdesh* and wasn't
מקדיש *makdish* it...
I mean
what was... I think the base construction...
right, right, right, right...
when they they set them they wanted they were actually going to
use them, they didn't want to make them הקדש *hekdesh* because people
might accidentally lean on them while they're...
right, right, right, I'm glad you remember that. But what I'm trying
to remember is was that a case where they were owned by
הקדש *hekdesh* until that or were they not they were owned by
הקדש *hekdesh* but they didn't have קדושה *kedushah*? I have to check,
I don't remember. But you are correct that, so you might be
right, that might exactly be an example of that. There are some
examples where stuff could be owned by הקדש *hekdesh* and not have
קדושה *kedushah*. So that would be an easier way of understanding this.
Not that we would have allowed you to, you know, compromise the
קדושה *kedushah*, but it was just an issue of ownership then maybe
we'd have allowed you to take it. I'll check up that case,
thank you for mentioning that. That's, I think you might be right.
Okay, let's take a look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*. אלא ella, מאן
דאמר גזל גוי מותר *Ella man d'amar gezel goy mutar*. So תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* says פירש בקונטרס דבקרייא בהגוזל ומאכיל *pirush bekuntres debikraya be-Hagozel
Umachil*. The discussion in בבא קמא kama. *Bava Kamma* whether גזל גוי
*gezel goy* is מותר *mutar*. וקשיא דהתם אפילו מאן דשרי לא שרי
אלא ella אפקעת הלואתו *Vekashyah dehasam afilu man deshari lo shari ela
afka'at halva'ato*. But there, the conclusion of that גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* there rejects the opinion that גזל גוי *gezel goy*
is מותר *mutar*. That's important. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* raises it as
a הוה אמינא *hava amina* but that סוגיא sugya. *sugya* basically says
nobody holds it's מותר *mutar*. At most what's allowed is אפקעת הלואתו
*afka'at halva'ato*, which also isn't great, but it's not straight-out theft. Okay.
אבל גזילה ממש מודה כולי עלמא דאסור *Aval gezeila mamash modeh kuli
alma de'asur*. אלא אומר ר"י *Ella
omer Ri*, so where is the opinion that says that ממש *mamash*
פוסק'נס *paskins* that it's מותר *mutar*? אלא אומר ר"י דפליגי לקמן במכילתין
*Ella omer Ri depaligi lekaman bemachiltin*, איכא דשרי גזילה ממש *ika deshari
gezeila mamash*.
We're going to see later towards the end of the מסכת *masechet*
there will be that opinion. So there actually is an opinion that
straight-out גזל *gezel* is מותר *mutar*.
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says, ואם תאמר
למאן דאמר גזל גוי מותר מאי עביד ליה לקרא דוחשב עם קונהו
*ve-im tomar le-man d'amar gezel goy mutar mai avid lei likra devehishav
im koneyhu*, דדרשינן בכל הבתרא ידקדק עם קונהו שלא יגזלנו ולא יבוא
עליו בעקיפין *de-darshinan bekol habatra yedakdek im koneyhu shelo yigzelenu velo yavo
alav ba'akifin*.
So there the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says by this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
of that when you're sort of redeeming a יהודי *Yehudi* that was
bought as a slave by a גוי *goy*, you have to be
precise when in your dealings with the גוי *goy*, which seems to
be very clear that you're not allowed to steal. דדרשינן התם דגזל
גוי אסור asur *de-darshat hasham de-gezel goy asur*. וליכא למימר דשרי ליה
דקרא איירי כשיידם תקיפה על עצמן *Velika lemeimar deshari lei dekara ayiri
kesheyadam tekifa al atzman*, blah blah blah.
I'm going to skip that. ויש לומר *Veyeish lomar*, so about five
lines from the bottom of that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, דהיכא דאיכא חילול
השם מודה דאסור *deheicha de'ika chillul Hashem modeh de'asur*, שהכותי בטח עליו
ונושא ונותן עמו והוי חילול השם אם היוצא בחזקה קודם היובל
*shehakuti batach alav venose venoten imo vehavei chillul Hashem im hayotze bechazaka
kodem hayovel*. That maybe the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is אסור'ינג *assuring* it
not from the perspective of גזל גוי *gezel goy*. Technically גזל גוי
*gezel goy* is מותר *mutar*, but the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is prohibiting
cheating or whatever, scheming in that case because he'll realize it and
it'll lead to חילול השם *chillul Hashem*. So anyway, obviously this is
a deep problem that there is an opinion that גזל גוי *gezel
goy* is מותר *mutar* and that at most we're going to make
it אסור *asur* because it'll get discovered and found out. But nevertheless,
the important thing also from this תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is that the
dominant סוגיא *sugya* about גזל גוי *gezel goy*, which is in בבא
קמא *Bava Kamma*, basically doesn't even acknowledge the opinion that it's מותר
*mutar*, rejects the possibility that it's מותר *mutar*. It's only like this
small voice in this גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* that puts it back on
the table that opinion. Okay, so back to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Oh okay,
that's true. So back to so we haven't seen it yet so
it doesn't exist. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this,
okay, ואכלת *ve'achalta*, back to five lines from the bottom, we're continuing
to דרשן *darshan* the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. So if you shall eat
grapes, ואכלת ולא מוצץ, but you can't suck it out because presumably
as תוספות Tosafot says the point is that it's like, I mean,
that's שתיה, shtiya, that's not אכילה. achila. Okay, which is very funny.
I mean some people that's just like the way they they like
to eat grapes. So, you know, if they just like to suck
out the middle, I assume it doesn't mean you can't peel it
and eat the flesh without the skin, but I assume it means
you can't basically like squeeze it. Okay. I'm working in the yeah
like pressing grapes
and I can't take a
couple.
Well yeah that's an interesting question that's after it's been harvested. See
all of this is בשעת גמר מלאכה, b'shat gmar melacha, so anything
that's בשעת גמר מלאכה b'shat gmar melacha is not a liquid, right?
So anything that's growing from the ground. Okay but it is funny
it does seem like a relatively arbitrary distinction unless the point is
that no the whole point is that you're like snacking incidentally. Once
you start processing it, squeezing it, creating grape juice, you're not it's
not just like a type of snacking you're doing incidentally. Of course
if you're sucking it out you're not taking them and you know
whatever, but nevertheless maybe that's the line. It's only like an immediate
type of an eating. Okay.
ענבים, Anavim, grapes, ולא ענבים ודבר אחר, v'lo anavim v'davar acher, not
together with something else. What does that mean? So רש"י Rashi so
you could I would have thought it meant like if I'm harvesting
grapes and growing right near the grapes is an apple tree I
can't say oh I'm working on the grapes I'm going to take
an apple. Okay but רש"י Rashi says it's not what it means.
רש"י Rashi says what it means is don't add like some salt
to your grapes or don't add something else which'll make it easier
for you to eat a lot of it, okay? Like you know
I I wonder like are you allowed to drink together with it?
Like if you're drinking right you're able to eat more. Okay so
it says no no no you know you have to eat that's
the natural type of thing. You can't basically set up you sort
of like figure out a strategy that you can you know eat
as much as possible. It does say שבעך sav'echa till your full
but nevertheless okay. What if you put it
like on a sandwich in which case they'd be less?
No you can't put it on a sandwich that's דבר אחר. davar
acher. That doesn't matter once we apparently once we say the הלכה
halacha we say you know that's the הלכה. halacha. Anyway sometimes that's
not true sometimes if you put things anyway whatever.
But okay moving
on
okay ולא דבר כנפשך v'lo davar k'nafshecha as you desire. כנפש k'nefesh
now this line is the line that we're going to spend most
of the time on today כנפש של בעל הבית כך נפשו של
פועל, k'nefesh shel ba'al habayit kach nafsho shel po'el, just like the
owner is the worker. What does it mean? מה נפשו אוכל ופטור
אף נפשו של פועל אוכל ופטור. ma nafsho ochel u'patur af nafsho
shel po'el ochel u'patur. The same way when you eat grapes in
your field before the processing is done you are not obligated in
תרומה ומעשר, teruma u'ma'aser, it's not yet גמר מלאכה gmar melacha and
we'll that's what we're going to focus on in a minute. So
therefore when he eats also the processing isn't done he doesn't have
to take תרומה ומעשר. teruma u'ma'aser. So it sounds like obviously if
you're telling me it's not yet the time for תרומה ומעשר teruma
u'ma'aser of course he doesn't have to. So the חידוש chidush is
we're going to find out that if you however if you sold
the grapes, the person who bought them and is taking them in
the field okay might have to take תרומה ומעשר teruma u'ma'aser right
then and there or at least we say can't eat without taking
תרומה ומעשר teruma u'ma'aser okay. So why that should be a difference
if it's not yet the time for תרומה ומעשר teruma u'ma'aser why
it should matter if it's you if it's the worker if it's
somebody who bought it we'll see about all of that in a
minute. But that's the basic דרשה derasha here.
So if you sold the grapes then aren't they eating from somebody
else's grapes essentially?
No no no it's just saying you don't treat the worker as
somebody who purchased the grapes. If he was somebody who purchased the
grapes he'd have to take תרומה ומעשר teruma u'ma'aser but he's not
somebody who purchased grapes so he doesn't have to.
But if you sold all your crops whatever it is right? Yeah.
You know but what are you doing hiring a worker to work
on them?
I know but I'm hired to like you know pick it right?
I don't understand you're picking somebody's crop if he's hiring you you
can pick his grapes. Okay moving moving on. Okay so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay so the basic point is that if
even if if you sold it to somebody and they were taking
the grapes they would have they couldn't eat it without תרומה ומעשר.
teruma u'ma'aser. But the פועל po'el is considered like you, he's not
considered like somebody who bought it and therefore he doesn't have to
take תרומה ומעשר. teruma u'ma'aser. So what the difference is going to
be between you and somebody who bought it we'll see in a
minute. Okay so שבעך sav'echa your fill ולא אכילה גסה v'lo achila
gassa you can't force feed you know eat beyond your stuff yourself
beyond your fill.
But that's אסור anyway well that's true.
ואל כליך לא תתן v'el kelyecha lo titen don't put in your
vessel in order to like eat later בשעה שאתה נותן לכליו של
בעל הבית אתה אוכל ובשעה שאי אתה נותן לכליו של בעל הבית
אי אתה אוכל. b'shaa she'ata noten l'kelyo shel ba'al habayit ata ochel
u'v'shaa she'ee ata noten l'kelyo shel ba'al habayit ee ata ochel. So
this basically is you can only do it while you're in the
middle of working okay so as you're placing it into it sort
of inferring that you're not putting into your vessel you're putting into
your owner's vessel. So in the time when you're in the middle
of harvesting you eat not when that's not the time so that
tells you that it's while you're working that it's the time of
גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, not a time of גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha,
only when the stuff is sort of being harvested and picked okay
so
so now the גמרא Gemara, says like this okay one minute okay
דאמר רבי ינאי d'amar Rabbi Yannai so says רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai
אין הטבל מתחייב במעשר. ein hatevel mitchayev b'ma'aser. Now we're going to
focus in on this issue about when are food חייב chayav in
תרומה ומעשר teruma u'ma'aser and when I might have thought that why
I might have thought a פועל po'el would be חייב chayav difference
between a פועל po'el and somebody who purchases it.
דאמר רבי ינאי d'amar Rabbi Yannai אין הטבל מתחייב במעשר ein hatevel
mitchayev b'ma'aser הטבל hatevel is not obligated in מעשר ma'aser עד שיראה
פני הבית ad sheyirei pnei habayit until it's brought into the house.
So basically the point is like this there's two things for food
to be חייב chayav in תרומה ומעשר. teruma u'ma'aser. When we're talking
about a פועל poel eating
when it's being harvested, when it's being picked from the ground. The
גמר מלאכה gmar melacha of תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros is a different
stage when it basically is what it sounds like, the standard processing
is done, okay, so the גמרא Gemara will say let's say if
you're picking vegetables it means you've torn off all of the you
know the what do you call it like you know the hair
that grows from it and you know twigs or whatever not twigs
not veg anyway whatever you know the type of you know you
clean it off so now you're basically done now
you're basically ready to like ship it to market okay. If it's
grain it actually is a much later time it's after it's like
threshed and winnowed and put in a and put in a mound
and smoothed over. If it's olives or grapes so if you're planning
on basically eating olives or grapes then it might be right away.
But if you're basically turning it into wine or olive oil then
it's only after it's pressed and it's converted and so on. Okay
so things are basically after the whole processing is done and it's
basically ready to ship to market and you know might be some
trivial stuff like rinsing it off is not whatever but basically the
processing is done. So number one is you need גמר מלאכה gmar
melacha okay. Number two is now you and this is what our
גמרא Gemara is focusing on you need something else called it has
to be קובע. koveia. It has to do something that's like fixes
it sort of not just גמר מלאכה gmar melacha but something else
that basically says it's done. What are the things that are קובע?
koveia? The basic thing that's קובע koveia which is what our גמרא
Gemara is introducing is ראיית פני הבית. reiyat pnei habayit. It has
to be brought into the house. It also might be as we're
going to see brought into your חצר. chatzer Your חצר chatzer is
your yard not to be confused with your שדה sadeh your field
which is where it's growing. Okay so it's growing out in the
field you process it or whatever it's only חייב chayav once it's
brought into the house or once it's brought into your front yard.
Okay there are other types of things as well. The thing that's
going to be relevant for us because we're talking here about the
difference between a פועל poel and a purchaser is מכר mecher is
קובע. koveia. So if I sell it to somebody in the field
after the processing is done because I've now transferred ownership now they
can't eat it without תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'ma'asros. Other things that are
קובע koveia for example is cooking it is קובע. koveia. שבת Shabbos
is קובע. koveia. Figure that out. Okay but anyway we're not going
to deal with all of those. We're basically going to deal with
ראיית פני הבית reiyat pnei habayit or slash
החצר hachatzer and B the issue of מכר mecher which is going
to be relevant. So it's two things גמר מלאכה gmar melacha plus
something that's called קובע. koveia. And the basic thing that's קובע koveia
מן התורה min haTorah is what we're going to discuss is ראיית
פני הבית reiyat pnei habayit or ראיית פני החצר. reiyat pnei hachatzer.
Yes Charlie?
Let me review, ראיית פני הבית reiyat pnei habayit doesn't that apply
to מעשר ma'aser and תרומה terumah is actually usually given at the
threshing floor or in the mill?
So so תרומה terumah
so you can give it earlier that's true I mean you know
the גמרא Gemara? speaks about the people coming to the גורן goren
or whatever but the איסור issur to eat right is not until
you know is actually yeah exactly.
But for מכר mecher though I the seller have to take תרומות
ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros right? Meaning it's not an obligation on the purchaser.
Yes it is.
So if I want to buy a hundred from your field a
hundred barrels do I assume the loss of תרומות ומעשרות? terumos u'ma'asros?
Yeah you assume the loss.
No I mean if you know it's טבל tevel and we haven't
made any other stipulation and you're buying it as טבל tevel and
you have to understand that. Yeah. Now we actually will get to
an interesting discussion about the obligation of a buyer. Well okay so
you shouldn't be doing that but you're asking if you did. Okay
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So אמר רבי
ינאי Amar Rabbi Yannai אין הדבר מתחייב במעשר עד שיראה פני הבית.
ein hadavar mitchayev b'ma'aser ad sheyeira'eh pnei habayit.
Okay it's not obligated until it's brought into the house sees the
inside of the house. שנאמר Shene'emar as it says ביערתי הקודש מן
הבית bi'arti hakodesh min habayit
I have destroyed it from the house which means that the obligations
about it begin only because it's in the house. רבי יוחנן אמר
Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabbi Yochanan said אפילו חצר קובעת afilu chatzer kova'as
even if it's brought into the yard it is there's the word
it's קובע. koveia. שנאמר Shene'emar yeah he disagrees. שנאמר Shene'emar תוספות Tosafot
says that's explicitly מפורש meforash משנה mishna that חצר chatzer is קובע
koveia but the question is is that דאורייתא d'Oraisa דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. שנאמר Shene'emar ואכלו בשעריך
ושבעו v'achlu bish'arecha v'save'u
in your gates. So if it's in your gates city gates right
that would be like your חצר chatzer. because you know the fields
are outside of the city. Okay so anyway so that's where the
and that speaks about ונתת ללוי לגר ליתום ולאלמנה ואכלו בשעריך ושבעו.
v'nasata laleivi lager layasom v'la'almana v'achlu bish'arecha v'save'u.
That's giving of the מעשר ma'aser so that is in your gates
okay so it's even if it has not yet got into your
house. ורבי יוחנן נמי הכתיב V'Rabbi Yochanan nami hach'shiv but Rabbi Yochanan
doesn't it also say מן הבית min habayit that from the house?
אמר לך Amar lach חצר דומיא דבית. chatzer dumya d'bayis.
It doesn't have to be the house. House teaches us what type
of a yard we're talking about. מה בית משתמר Mah bayis mishtamer
the same way a house is protected אף חצר משתמר af chatzer
mishtamer so it has to be a yard that's protected that has
a fence around it or something because a yard that anyone has
access to that's not acceptable. It has to be a yard like
a house. Okay so that's the idea of yard. רבי ינאי נמי
Rabbi Yannai nami now Rabbi Yannai who says only a house הכתיב
בשעריך hach'shiv bish'arecha doesn't it say your gates? ההוא מיבעי ליה Hahu
mibayei lei
that's coming to teach you דמעיילי ליה דרך שער d'ma'ayilei lei derech
sha'ar that you have to bring it through your front door לאפוקי
דרך גגות וקרפיפות le'apokei derech gagot v'karfifot
as opposed to if you brought it through the roof or through
type of. type of a, what's a קרפיף? karfif? It's a balcony,
what is it, a portico? You never remember what that is.
I don't know.
Maybe if you put it... maybe if you go through the window.
I know, I just don't remember exactly what a קרפיף karfif is.
What do they say a קרפף karpef is there? Do they have
English?
What? Oh. Okay. All
right. Anyway, whatever it is. Not through the front door. דלא. Delo.
That would not be obligated. So the גמרא Gemara says מתיב רבי
חנינא. Masiv Rabbi Chanina. Okay, so that's the first debate now. What
that has to do with us, we don't even know yet. Okay,
but that's the debate about does it have to be... backyard. Okay,
there you go. All right. Has to go through your front door,
not your backyard. Excellent. Okay, מתיב רבי חנינא. Masiv Rabbi Chanina. So
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said...
חזא. Chaza. Okay, כנשך. Kenash'cha. Now, now we're going to see why
we're bringing it in. Because we're going to try to challenge this
idea based on the דרשה derasha here about the פועל. poel. Okay,
כנשך. Kenash'cha. כנשך של פועל. Ke-nash'cha shel poel. Just like you is
the worker. מה נשך אוכל ופטור אף נשך של פועל אוכל ופטור.
Mah nash'cha ochel u-patur af nash'cha shel poel ochel u-patur.
You eat without having to take... without having to take תרומות ומעשרות,
terumot u-ma'asrot, your worker does. You're out in the field. All right,
so what's the issue? So the גמרא Gemara says הלוקח חייב. Ha-loke'ach
chayav. The only reason you'd have to tell me that the worker
is exempt means that somebody else out in the field would be
חייב. chayav. Okay, so as I told you, the implication is the
worker is not yet... hasn't purchased it. He has a right to
eat it. But if somebody actually purchased it and they were out
in the field, they'd have to... they couldn't eat it without תרומות
ומעשרות. terumot u-ma'asrot. So now the question is going to be: why
would you ever have to take תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot out in
the field? It's not yet brought into your house or to your
yard. That seems to indicate that the obligation of תרומות ומעשרות terumot
u-ma'asrot can exist without this ראיית פני הבית. re'iyat pnei ha-bayit. Right?
At least for somebody who purchased it. So what's going to happen
with that? Okay, by the way, I just want to pause for
a moment and say that in the middle of these big תוספות
Tosafot in which he's trying to figure various things out about this,
תוספות Tosafot raises an important question about this issue about the worker
eating, which is, because the idea that worker's not like a purchaser.
When the worker is eating, is the worker eating the owner's food?
Or is the point that it basically is his? Right? Is it
like he has a right to eat the owner's food? Or is
the idea that he actually takes possession of it?
Okay. Somewhat of a קניין kinyan in
that. Exactly.
His picking it, he's picking it to pop it in his mouth,
is he has a right to eat the owner's or is he
actually eating... well, some of the issue has to be with issues
about this, about purchase and תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot or whatever. But
I just wanted to put out that conceptual question. So anyway, let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. כנשך של פועל מה נשך אוכל
ופטור. Ke-nash'cha shel poel mah nash'cha ochel u-patur. Wait a minute. אוכל
ופטור הלוקח חייב. Ochel u-patur ha-loke'ach chayav. Now, so it's possible, says
the גמרא, Gemara that you would be חייב chayav out in the
field, okay, without either of these things, ראיית פני הבית re'iyat pnei
ha-bayit or ראיית פני חצר. re'iyat pnei chatzer. So it sounds like
these things are not absolutely required. So the גמרא Gemara.
says, a field? I thought we said it was some... according to
רב ינאי Rav Yannai or whoever it was.
No, a שדה sadeh is not a חצר. chatzer I said that
already. Do not confuse a yard, your front yard, with a field.
A field is outside the city where the stuff grows. So the
גמרא Gemara says אף נשך של פועל. Af nash'cha shel poel. So
הלוקח חייב. Ha-loke'ach chayav. מאי לאו בשדה? Mai lav be-sadeh? Are we
not talking about that it's out in the field? And therefore you
see you don't need these things. Even out in the field you
could be חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u-ma'asrot. So the גמרא
Gemara says, now the funny thing is, and what part of these
תוספות Tosafot are figuring out, is like what is bothering the גמרא?
Gemara Because דרבנן, de-rabbanan, as I said to you before, the basic
structure is the
following: דאורייתא, de-oraita, בית bayit or חצר chatzer. is קובע. kove'a. But
דרבנן, de-rabbanan, one of the things that's קובע kove'a is מקח, mekach,
is purchasing it. So like that's the whole answer. You're out in
the field, it's not yet obligated, you and the worker don't have
to... can eat it without תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u-ma'asrot, but if you
sell it, that דרבנן de-rabbanan creates a חיוב chiyuv of תרומות ומעשרות.
terumot u-ma'asrot. The problem is is that, you know, we're דרשנינג darshaning
it from פסוקים, pesukim, so that seems like you can't introduce a
rabbanic idea, it has to be working on a biblical level. Okay,
so that might be part of the issue. Okay, but that's the
גמרא'ס... Gemara's... but anyway, the גמרא Gemara is saying how could it
be that somebody is חייב, chayav, it doesn't have ראיית פני הבית?
re'iyat pnei ha-bayit? So the גמרא Gemara says אף
נשך של פועל, Af nash'cha shel poel, so הלוקח חייב. Ha-loke'ach chayav.
מאי לאו בשדה? Mai lav be-sadeh? Doesn't this mean in a field?
So what's going to... how could you be חייב chayav in a
field? There's no ראיית פני הבית. re'iyat pnei ha-bayit. אמר רב פפא
הכא בתאנה העומדת בגינה ונופה נוטה לחצר עסקינן. Amar Rav Pappa hacha
bite'enah ha-omedet be-ginah ve-nofah noteh le-chatzer askinan. So this is going to
be one of these crazy cases. All of תוספות Tosafot says the
whole thing is לאו דוקא. lav davka. But here's what תוספות Tosfos
says: you've got your tree that's in the garden, okay, that's not
your yard. Again, the place where the stuff is growing is not
your yard. So you could have a שדה sadeh that's not outside
the city, it could be a nice little garden that you have
nearby. You've got your tree in your garden and it's the foliage
is bending into your חצר. chatzer, Okay, ולמאן דאמר לבית לבית. U-le-man
de-amar le-bayit le-bayit. And if you say the house, it's bending into
the house. So basically, through a window.
I guess that's
exactly, I just have to draw
this. Here's your house, here's your front yard, okay, I guess you
can draw a little window here, okay, and then over here you've
got... so this is your חצר, chatzer okay, and this is your
גינה. ginah.
Wait, seriously, where's the wall? Is the wall around?
Yeah, I know, I know. Now you're asking me to draw 3D.
Okay, anyway, okay, and here's the tree and the tree right, whatever,
goes from there and its... reaching over so here you you like
stick out your hand and you take it. So you've got a
פני הבית p'nei habayit there, okay, or you're standing here and you're
taking it. Okay, now why do you need that crazy case? So
רש״י Rashi says you need רש״י Rashi which actually is what it
more sounds like in the גמרא Gemara. says you need it because
basically what you need to do is you need it to go
from where it's growing into the חצר chatzer or from where it's
growing into the house. Okay, and that's why you have to start
it out in essentially this which is the שדה sadeh and go
in and that obligates it. תוספות Tosfos, though does not like that
because תוספות Tosfos, anyway says I don't understand when you're doing this
you're not taking it in through the front door, right? What does
it say? So how does that work? If you're just say you're
supposed to go into, you gotta go in through the front door.
And when you go into the חצר chatzer you gotta go in
through the שער shaar of the חצר chatzer. the main open. So
תוספות Tosfos says this whole thing is לאו דוקא. lav davka. It
really just it's just that it would be bizarre to have an
apple tree growing in your front yard so they described it this
way. But they could just as easily have said that the apple
tree is growing in your front yard in your front yard. And
it has nothing to do with taking it from the חצר. chatzer.
Okay, but whatever it is, that's how we somehow have solved that
it's now in your house or now in the חצר. chatzer, But
still, what is the difference between the owner and the worker on
the one hand and the purchaser on the other? So let's read
the next line. Okay, so let's read the next line. So הכא
בתאנה העומדת בגינה ונופה נוטה לחצר עסקינן, hacha biteina ha-omedes begina venofah
noteh lechatzer askinan, okay, so a fig tree that's standing in the
garden and it's growing over into your yard. למאן דאמר לבית לבית,
leman de-amar labayis labayis, and one says it's going into the house,
it's reaching into the house. So and that's why it does have
a ראיית פני הבית, re'iyas p'nei habayis, it does have a ראיית
פני החצר, re'iyas p'nei hachatzer, it's in the חצר, chatzer it's in
the בית. bayis. אי הכי i hachi says the גמרא Gemara בעל
הבית נמי ניחייב. ba'al habayis nami nichayiv. So okay, so if you're
actually having that קבע, keva, why isn't the homeowner חייב? chayav? Why
isn't the פועל po'el חייב? chayav? If it is going into the
house. So the גמרא Gemara says בעל הבית עיניו בתאנתו ולוקח עיניו
בנופכו. ba'al habayis einav bite'inato velokei'ach einav benofcho. A בעל הבית ba'al
habayis looks at the tree and the purchaser looks at the fruit.
Okay now, what does that mean? Well let's just describe what it
means. It means I'm the homeowner or similarly you're my worker, and
the job is to pick all the fruit off the tree. So
from our perspective we don't care about this immediate fruit and where
it is, we care about the fact that the whole tree has
to get harvested. You the purchaser if you're buying like one apple
from me, you don't care where the tree is, how much apples
have to be picked, you bought your one apple and you care
about the apple right here. Now what difference does that make? So
it depends what you think is going on here. For רש״י Rashi
who says that what's going on is that we needed it to
go from the field into the house, okay, so or you know,
it has a ראיית פני הבית. re'iyas p'nei habayis. So רש״י Rashi
says like this: For you, the owner or the worker if your
job is to go pick all the apples and here you're coming
into the חצר chatzer to get some of the stuff or whatever,
so your job is to pick it. You are conceptually seeing yourself
in the field, not in the house. Yes you are picking it
here, but you know you have to go and finish all the
picking and really the apple tree is out in the garden. So
even though physically you are right here, conceptually and that's where the
apple is, your relationship is not to the apple. Your relationship is
to the tree. You have to take all the stuff from the
tree. It's not about this one apple and therefore if I asked
you where are you harvesting the fruit, the answer is not in
the yard. The answer is in the field because that's my job
to harvest. Now that read actually fits very nicely with classic גמרות
Gemaras where actually this is a classic sort of case in the
גמרא. Gemara The trunk is here, the foliage is there, where are
you like you know where is it? You know and you could
have it like it's growing in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and the
foliage is over the boundary in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz and this
apple is in the line on past the חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
line but the trunk is here, is it חייב בתרומות ומעשרות chayav
in terumos uma'asros or פטור? patur? What if it's the reverse? You
know so the גמרא Gemara. likes playing with that idea and sort
of saying where conceptually is your location? And this works perfectly. It
says if I'm buying something and I'm in your yard, I just
care about the apple, I don't care about the tree. So where
am I? I'm in your yard and I have an apple in
your yard. So that has an obligation of תרומות ומעשרות, terumos uma'asros,
okay, because that has the חצר chatzer. or the בית. bayis. If
however I'm the worker or the owner, I am not conceptually in
the yard. I am conceptually out in the field where where the
tree is really located. And therefore it is not yet חייב בתרומות
ומעשרות. chayav in terumos uma'asros. So that's why the owner and the
worker are not חייב chayav and that's why the what do you
call it the purchaser is חייב. chayav. That's the way רש״י Rashi
explains it. תוספות Tosfos says it different. תוספות Tosfos says we really
don't even need there to be a yard here. There could all
be one חצר. chatzer That the גמרא Gemara was just saying that
for fun. Okay he doesn't say for fun. Okay but he says
it didn't really mean it. And he says here's the difference. The
difference is תוספות Tosfos introduces a new idea. The difference is גמר
מלאכה gemar melacha is not is not measured by each fruit, okay?
It's measured by "I'm done with the job." So, okay, like let's
say, right? I actually am picking apples or whatever I'm picking and
I'm out in the field and I'm picking apples and it's my
job and I have to pick, you know, thousands of apple trees,
okay? And I take one apple back with me into the house.
Is it חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות? terumos umasros? It got picked,
it's ראיית פני הבית, reiyas pnei habayis, but do we judge it
by a fruit by fruit or do we look at the whole
job? So תוספות Tosfos says we look at the whole job. Okay,
if I'm the owner or if I'm the worker. So therefore, says
תוספות, Tosfos, I mean it's totally not this interesting crossing a boundary
line, for the owner or the worker, picking one fruit is not
חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros. He's not done. אינו בטנא
eino batenah means you got the whole tree to pick. Okay, so
it's not where the tree is located, it means you're not done,
you got the whole tree to pick. Whereas the purchaser, if I
only want one apple, I'm done. All my my whole interest is
the one apple. I bought the one apple. So can't he eat
the last apple? No תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros. Why does he why
does he need that whole scenario? He doesn't. He whatever, so he
says because the גמרא Gemara does the גמרא Gemara would find it
strange for a tree to be growing in your front yard, so
why because you know, so it had it growing in the garden
because nobody has apple trees growing in their front yard. I don't
mean apple, the גמרא Gemara has fig trees. Whatever. רש"י Rashi is
certainly the פשט pshat of the גמרא. Gemara Okay, but of course
so again to review, רש"י Rashi says the issue is what are
you in the yard or are you in the house... are you
in the field or are you in the house yard? So if
you're the purchaser, you're in the house yard because that's physically where
you are, that's all you care about. If you're the owner or
the worker, your mind is out in the field because you have
the you're focusing on the tree. And therefore there's no ראיית פני
הבית. reiyas pnei habayis. According to תוספות, Tosfos the question is, is
the job done or not? If you're the owner or the worker,
the job isn't done and there's no גמר מלאכה. gemar melacha. If
you're the purchaser and this is all you wanted to buy, then
the job is done. Okay, but so that's how they sort of
see the difference. Yes? But according to רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos
then, he'd actually for instance, in another instance, he I can't take
the last one, the job is done, right? I can't take the
last one? What do you mean you can't take the last... the
last apple of harvesting this tree today? Yes? But I can't take
the last one because that's... if you pick the last well, no,
you need ראיית פני הבית reiyas pnei habayis then. It has to
be the job has to be done and there has to be
ראיית פני הבית. reiyas pnei habayis. Okay, but anyway the interesting thing
is that להלכה, lehalacha, none none of this is true. Because להלכה
lehalacha we say that the and it's bizarre why the גמרא Gemara
ignored this, that the difference between why purchasing makes a difference is
that מדרבנן miderabbanan purchasing creates it like ראיית פני הבית. reiyas pnei
habayis. It's another way to create this issue of קבע. keva. But
the גמרא Gemara isn't dealing with that presumably because the גמרא Gemara
is trying to figure this out on a דאורייתא deoraisa level. So
on a דאורייתא deoraisa level, why should it matter if you purchased
or you didn't? So it creates this different scenario where you are
or whether the job is done. But on a מדרבנן miderabbanan level,
purchasing acts as a substitute for ראיית פני הבית. reiyas pnei habayis.
Okay, so now let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא
Gemara says, now that you sort of said the case is about
purchasing because we're all explaining this פסוק pasuk about the worker, contrasting
the worker to the purchaser, so we're dealing on a דאורייתא deoraisa
level. So now that you're saying on a דאורייתא deoraisa level, a
purchaser is חייב chayav in this scenario and a worker is exempt,
so the גמרא Gemara. says how can somebody who purchases תרומות ומעשרות
terumos umasros ever really be חייב? chayav? So the גמרא Gemara says
ולוקח מן התורה מי מיחייב? veloke'ach min hatorah mi michayav? One minute,
if we're talking on a דאורייתא deoraisa level, so how could a
purchaser ever be חייב? chayav? Why? והתניא, vehatanya, it's taught in a
ברייתא, baraisa, מפני מה חרבו חנויות של בית הינו? mipnei mah charvu
chanuyos shel beis hino? Why did the stores of this place Beis
Hino get destroyed? שלש שנים קודם ירושלים, shalosh shanim kodem yerushalayim, three
years before Jerusalem. מפני שהעמידו דבריהם על דברי תורה mipnei shehe'emidu divreihem
al divrei torah because all they cared about was like they were
Karaites, all they cared about was doing the תורה Torah law, they
were did not really care about רבנן rabbanan law, okay, what does
it mean? שהיו אומרים, shehayu omerim, and here's the תורה Torah law
that they would apply: עשר תעשר, aser tayser, you shall surely take
מעשר, maaser, you know, עשר תעשר את כל תבואת זרעך, aser tayser
es kol tvuas zar'acha, the פסוק pasuk says שנה שנה ואכלת shanah
shanah veachalta and you shall eat, ולא מוכר. velo mocher. Okay, so
if you are planning on harvesting your fruit for for sale, not
for eating, you don't have an obligation of תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros.
So you're the seller, if you're selling it, you don't have an
obligation of taking תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros. Now, how about if you're
the buyer? So then they learned another דרשה: drasha: תבואת זרעך, tvuas
zar'acha, the grain of your seed, the seed you planted, ולא לוקח.
velo loke'ach. If you're a purchaser and it didn't you didn't grow
it, you don't have to take it. So it's great, that solves
my whole problem. You don't have to lose your whole profit margin.
Here's a way of never having to take תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros.
You know, you just do everything for sale, nothing for your own
eating. And when you buy... and I it was an interesting question,
let's say, could I do this, I'll sell it to you and
then buy it back from me? But let's say you're not go
there, okay. Here they were, they were in business, they were selling
it, and they made the they said okay, nobody has to take
תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros. And the גמרא Gemara, doesn't seem to contest
that on a תורה Torah level. It seems to say the problem
was was that מדרבנן miderabbanan they had to take it and they
were ignoring the מדרבנן miderabbanan obligation. מן התורה min hatorah only a
בעל הבית. baal habayis. So it sounds like... we'll discuss in a
minute, תוספות Tosfos seems to challenge a lot of other סוגיות. sugyos.
So I'll discuss it in a minute. But at least for now
it seems that מן התורה min hatorah the only person who takes
תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros. Or, or, or, or it's if I'm, I'm
a farmer, I'm a total wholesaler. I'm not going to eat any
of it. So I don't have to give it דאורייתא. de-raisa. I
sell it to you, you're the retailer, you're not going to eat
any of it. You don't have to. Only the customer. No, the
customer doesn't. Nobody has to. So then there would be no מעשר!
Maiser! Exactly. No תרומות ומעשרות Trumos and Maisros from a תורה perspective,
and the גמרא Gemara doesn't challenge this on anything that is sold.
It only applies to when you eat your own stuff. Okay, totally
radical. I'll discuss in a minute what תוספות Tosfos does, because obviously
that seems to violate a lot of other principles. Okay, but that's
what the גמרא Gemara seems to say. So now the גמרא Gemara
says if that's true, okay, מדרבנן mi-derabbanan you're חייב. chayav. But how
could the פסוק pasuk say a worker doesn't have to take and
a purchaser does? Right, we've already explained that the purchaser creates a
scenario of ראיית פני הבית reiyah pnei ha-bayis in this case. Fine,
but if it's purchased, you're telling me that a purchaser never has
to take תרומות ומעשרות. Trumos and Maisros. So the גמרא Gemara says
באותה שעה אלא סנומא be-osah sha'ah ella senuma fine, מדרבנן. mi-derabbanan. This
whole idea of contrasting the worker to the purchaser is a rabbinic
idea, דחייתא בעלמא. dachachta be'alma. And the verse is just a, you
know, a support. It's not a real הלכה. halacha. You're right. מן
התורה, Min ha-Torah, nobody has to take. The בעל הבית baal ha-bayis
and the worker because it's not yet ראיית פני הבית, reiyah pnei
ha-bayis, and the purchaser because a purchaser never has to take. So
this distinction between the worker and a purchaser is only at a
rabbinic level and that's not really what the פסוק pasuk is doing.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to say okay, so what
is the פסוק doing? But before we get to that, let me
just talk a minute about the purchaser. So you see, if you
I'm sure it did not escape your notice that the previous עמוד
amud was short because there was these big תוספות-in. Tosfos So one
תוספות Tosfos was this whole discussion I was dealing with, but the
other תוספות, Tosfos... the biggest תוספות is how can you say that
if you purchase grain you don't have to take תרומות ומעשרות? Trumos
and Maisros? It goes against so many different סוגיות. sugyos. So תוספות
says makes a distinction between when did you purchase the grain? Did
you purchase it before גמר מלאכה gmar melacha or after גמר מלאכה?
gmar melacha? Now, גמר מלאכה gmar melacha we're talking about, the you
know, the winnowing, the whatever. Okay, now, which way does that make
a difference? Okay, so תוספות goes has two opinions, directly opposite opinions.
One opinion says if you purchased it before גמר מלאכה gmar melacha
and then you did the גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, so then it's
your זרעך. zarecha. You're like the new owner, you saw it through
at that critical moment where it became grain חייב chayav in תרומות
ומעשרות, Trumos and Maisros, so then you have to take it. But
if you buy it after גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, you're exempt. Now,
according to that that means that still going to get you to
the reality that מדאורייתא mi-de'oraisa almost all the stuff that's sold is
exempt because people buy it after it's been processed. Okay, but that's
one distinction, at least it deals with some difficult סוגיות. sugyos. The
other distinction, which is is the opposite, which תוספות seems to, I
mean I don't know if תוספות prefers, but I prefer, not just
for practically but conceptually, which is if you the owner winnow it
and do the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha and so on, then then
you're the original owner, then it becomes חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות.
Trumos and Maisros. That then is a state that I will say
inheres in the grain itself. The grain, it was under my ownership,
I was still right, then I did the גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha,
the grain now is חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. Trumos and Maisros.
Now it doesn't matter who takes it. That's just a status now
of the grain. So you purchase it, you still have to take
it. The only exemption is that I went ahead I sold it
to you before גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. So a non-owner was the
one who was owning it when it hits that critical state, or
a non-grower I should say, that is exempt, okay, because only but
so but if the owner, the original owner is there at that
critical state it becomes חייב chayav and it remains חייב. chayav. That
is very nice because it certainly practically means that all the grain
that's sold you're going to be חייב chayav in, right, which is
what we assume. It's only a special case that somebody buys it
before the גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. It also parallels other ideas, for
example, ownership of a non-Jew exempts the grain from תרומות ומעשרות. Trumos
and Maisros. When does the ownership matter? If he owns it at
the time of גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. If he buys right, if
he owns
it at different times his ownership doesn't matter. So usually we say
that that
like a problematic
state is critical at that moment.
Okay, so according to this read this exemption of if somebody purchases
it they're
exempt is only if somebody if somebody purchased it before גמר מלאכה,
gmar melacha, after גמר מלאכה gmar melacha they remain חייב. chayav. Now
the question is why didn't the גמרא Gemara make one of those
distinctions? And the answer this and this is why it was relevant,
is that is it give me something, the answer is, the answer
is is that this is the question about when the, you know
sort of like about when the worker is considered to like purchase
it or not purchase it before גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, after גמר
מלאכה, gmar melacha, that gets into some of those interesting discussions about
you know when is it when is it considered to be the
worker's grain or is he just eating the בעל הבית's baal ha-bayis
and if it is his grain at what moment is it his
grain. So that gets into. If he owned it before גמר מלאכה
gmar melacha and sold it back to the Jew, before גמר מלאכה
gmar melacha it would not be a problem. It's only the ownership
at that critical moment of גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. It's not any
like any sliver of time. It has to be ownership when the
moment of obligation hits, which is the time of גמר מלאכה. gmar
melacha. That's when ownership, that's when the question of ownership is relevant.
Alright? So, yeah. If it's not tithed, it doesn't matter who owns
it, it's still טבל. tevel. Right! And there's a rather serious ceremony.
Exactly, which is why תוספות says once it's חייב, chayav, it doesn't
change just because somebody else bought it. So this answer yes, but
that answer is the much more deeply satisfying one. A, it means
that it's not crazy that everything sold is exempt. And number two,
conceptually, that's how we imagine it, that it's a status of the
food. So once the food has that status, it retains that status
regardless of who. But if you own it before it gets that
status, and seen as a different type of ownership, it will prevent
it from getting that status. Yes. Yeah, and somebody would be motivated
to buy the produce before גמר מלאכה gmar melacha because it might
be less expensive. Maybe, yeah. Yeah. A lot of produce are only
חייב chayav in tithes דרבנן derabanan in the first place. That's true
also. And there's an opinion ירושלמי Yerushalmi seems to accept that all
תרומה ומעשר terumah u'maaser are דרבנן. derabanan. Well, that's nowadays. Okay, so
let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says אלא,
okay, so that was the hard part of the גמרא, Gemara so
we all got through that, give yourselves a pat on the back.
אלא says the גמרא Gemara כנפשך למה אתא? kenafshecha lamah ata? If
כנפשך kenafshecha is not coming to tell you that a worker is
exempt and a purchaser is חייב, chayav, because a purchaser is not
חייב, chayav, what is it coming to tell you? לכדתניא: lichdetanya: כנפשך.
kenafshecha. מה נפשך אם חסמת פטור, mah nafshecha im chasamt patur, אף
פועל אם חסמת פטור. af poel im chasamt patur. Now we get
into an interesting discussion, which we're going to get into, is the
prohibition of לא תחסום שור בדישו. lo tachsom shor bedisho. Do not
muzzle an ox when it's threshing, which gets us not from the
harvesting, but the working on the stuff after it's been harvested, the
תלוש. talush. Okay, and we're going to learn out that a worker
has a right to eat from the stuff he works with if
he's working with it after it's been harvested, from the תלוש, talush,
from the prohibition of muzzling an ox. That's how we learn out
that a worker has a right even after it's been harvested. Okay,
but although that's who we learn it out from, if you do
muzzle your worker, okay, you actually prevent him, you make a stipulation,
you physically muzzle him, you tell him he's not allowed to eat,
whatever you tell him, you might be compromising his monetary rights because
he has a right to eat from it, you know, but you
do not transgress the prohibition of לא תחסום שור בדישו. lo tachsom
shor bedisho. That prohibition, from there we learn out he is allowed
to eat, but you do not actually transgress that לאו, lav, that
negative prohibition, only applies to an ox. It doesn't apply to a
worker. But didn't he say that the worker's only when you're before
the? No. Before when it's growing, it's at גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha,
and when it's been harvested, it's at שלא בשעת גמר מלאכה. shelo
bishat gmar melacha. Okay, and that we learn out from לא תחסום
שור בדישו. lo tachsom shor bedisho. Okay, so מה נפשך אם חסמת
פטור, mah nafshecha im chasamt patur, the same way you don't transgress
muzzling yourself, אף פועל אם חסמת פטור, af poel im chasamt patur,
you don't transgress—now you might be robbing the worker because he has
a right to eat, but you do not transgress the prohibition of
לא תחסום שור בדישו. lo tachsom shor bedisho. Okay, מתיב מר זוטרא.
masiv Mar Zutra. איזהו גורן למעשרות? eizehu goren lemaasros? Now we're still
not done. Okay, now you would have liked us, I would have
liked us to get on to the worker issue, but we still
have to finish our discussion about the idea of בית bayis and
חצר and which is קובע. koveia. Okay, so we're going to finish
that and then we're going to go back to the worker. So
מתיב מר זוטרא. masiv Mar Zutra. איזהו גורן למעשרות? eizehu goren lemaasros?
When is the moment where different types of things are considered obligated
in מעשר? maaser? בקישואים ובדלועים, bekishuim uvidluim, with like what is that,
cucumbers and gourds, okay, מי שיפקסו. mi sheyefaksu. So רש"י Rashi says
יפקסו yefaksu means like some type of the stem is pulled off,
although cucumbers don't have a stem. Do they? I don't know. Do
they? They do? Okay, so רש"י Rashi says it's like the stem
is pulled off. I don't know. What do I know from cucumbers?
It's the blossom. It's the blossom, stem. It's only what I see
in the supermarket. It seems to me that the תוספות... Okay, yeah.
I have six blossoms. Yeah, and the blossom's on there. The blossom's
on there when you pick it. So רש"י Rashi says it means
the blossom. The way I read the רמב"ם, Rambam, it sounds like
the רמב"ם Rambam was talking about that you remove some of the
hairs from the skin. I don't know if all things have those,
but the רמב"ם Rambam talks about like rubbing them on the surface
to get the hairs off. Anyway... It's just for a Greek word
that means hair or wool. Hair or wool, there you go. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says ואמר רבי אסי, ve'amar Rabbi Assi, מי
שינטל פיקס שלהם, mi sheyental pikas shelahem, when the פיקס, pikas, either
the blossom or the hairs, is removed. Now presumably, where are you
doing this? Out in the field. מה לאו מי שיפקסו אפילו בשדה?
mah lav mi sheyefaksu afilu basadeh? Out in the field and you
see it doesn't mean פני הבית pnei habayis or it doesn't mean
פני חצר. pnei chatzer. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, מי שיפקסו
בבית. lo, mi sheyefaksu babayis. No, no, no, it means you did
it and you brought them home. It doesn't mean that you did
it out in the field and it's still not חייב. chayav. So
the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי מי שיפקסו? עד שיפקסו. ee hachi
mi sheyefaksu? ad sheyefaksu. it would be violate. משיפסקו *mi-sheyipsiku* sounds like
it's a natural processing. You know, from the moment, from the moment
you do that, it's חייב *chayav*. The moment you do that, you're
out in the field. If you wanted to say not until, you
know, it was a much distant time you have to do this
and be in your house etc., you would have used the word
עד *ad*, which would have suggested not like the immediate moment but
like until a later time. Says גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it's an interesting
grammatical דיוק *diyuk*. Anyway, the גמרא *Gemara* says it sounds like you're
out in the field. It does not sound like you're in home.
It says no. אי תנא עד שיפסקו *ee tanna ad sheyipsiku* הוי
אמינא עד דגמר דפיקוסיאיהו *havai amina ad d'gmar depikusaihu*. If it said
עד *ad*, עד שיפסקו *ad sheyipsiku*, I would have thought you had
to do it complete, to completely remove all of the blossom, you
know, like not just beginning the process of removal but finishing the
process of removal. קמשמע לן *kamashman* משיפסקו *mi-sheyipsiku* which means מכי אתחולי
פקוסיאיהו *miki etchulei pikusaihu* when you begin the processing. But nevertheless it
has to be in the house. Okay, again, not anywhere near the
פשט peshat. *pshat*. The פשט peshat *pshat* is that it's out in
the field. But we're going to try again to prove this question
of does it have to come into the house or not. מתיב
מר זוטרא *masiv Mar Zutra*. So מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra* asked בדרבי
נחמן *ba'd'Rabbi Nachman*: גורן למעשר לחייב עליו משום טבל *goren l'maaser l'chayev
alav mishum tevel*? What is something's considered its threshing floor for מעשר
*maaser*? What is the state moment where it's חייב טבל *chayav tevel*?
משיגמור מלאכתו *mishe-yigmor melachto* when the work is done. ואיזו היא גמר
מלאכה gemar melacha, *ve-eizo hee gmar melacha*? What's the end of the
work? מלאכת הכנסתם *melachas hachnasasom* gathering it in. So now the גמרא
*Gemara* says מאי לאו הכנסתם אפילו בשדה *mai lav hachnasasom afilu basadeh*?
Doesn't that mean gathering it in the field, like making piles of
it out in the field? That's the normal gathering that gets done
with grain, right? You pile it all together. Says גמרא *Gemara* says
לא הכנסתם לבית *lo hachnasasom labayis*. No, once you bring it into
the house. Out in the field it's still not חייב *chayav*. So
you have all these things that sound like the חיוב *chiyuv* hits
in the field and we're saying no, no, no, that's גמר מלאכה
gemar melacha. *gmar melacha* but it still needs to come into the
house. Okay, at least it could be the חצר *chatzer*, right? It
could be the house. Okay, it could be the חצר *chatzer*, at
least according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. Why is it a funny
language? Yeah, according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* at least it could
be the... it could be the חצר *chatzer*. Okay, so the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this, ואיבעית אימא *v'iba'is eima*, now if you want
like it said and now we finally have a little bit of
a pull back, אימא כי קאמר רב ינאי *eima ki ka'amar Rav
Yannai*, when did רב ינאי *Rav Yannai* say bring it into the
house and maybe רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* about the חצר *chatzer*, בזיתים
וענבים דלאו בני גורן *bezaysim va'anavim d'lav bnei goren*, olives and grapes
that you're not making into grape juice or into wine or olive
oil. Because those things, there's nothing to do. You could say apples,
right? Okay, except that apples would not be biblically obligated. Olives and
grapes, the only thing that's biblically obligated is grain and wine and
the olive oil, דגן תירוש ויצהר *dagan tirosh v'yitzhar*. So interestingly this
גמרא *Gemara* makes it sound like olive oil and wine is biblically
obligated. Are grapes and olives also biblically obligated if you don't turn
it into that? So this גמרא *Gemara* makes it sound like it
is. Anyway, so it says they're talking about olives and grapes, so
you pick your grape, you're done. What's the גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha*?
So those things that don't have any other גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha*,
they're not חייב *chayav* until they're brought into the house. Everything else
that has a whole processing, all that evidence we've brought that sounds
like the גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha* out in the field is still
חייב *chayav* is חייב *chayav* without coming into the house. Those are
things that have a real processing to be done. Joe Safran, I
think. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, okay, so ואיבעית אימא כי קאמר
רב ינאי בזיתים וענבים דלאו בני גורן *v'iba'is eima ki ka'amar Rav
Yannai bezaysim va'anavim d'lav bnei goren*. They're talking about grapes and olives
that don't have like a threshing floor. They don't have a processing.
So those things are חייב *chayav* when they're brought into the house.
דלאו בני גורן נינהו *d'lav bnei goren ninhu*. אבל חטים ושעורים *aval
chitin us'orin*, wheat and barley, גורן בהדיא כתיב Ksiv, ביה *goren behedya
kesiv bei*, the Torah explicitly talks about the threshing floor. So those
things would be חייב *chayav* in the threshing floor at the גמר
מלאכה *gmar melacha* and even before... even without being brought into the
house. Okay, so this is a nice conceptual distinction. It deals with
a lot of the evidence. Problem is that a lot of other
גמרות *Gemaros* and the הלכה halacha *halacha* says no, you always need
ראיית פני הבית *reiyas p'nei habayis* or you always read ראיית פני
חצר *reiyas p'nei chatzer*. It's not enough to be done with it
out in the field, you actually need like a bringing in. Now
I don't really fully understand that because let's say there's stuff like
strawberries that you never even bring into the חצר *chatzer*. You arrange
with the retailer or the wholesaler, whatever, he picks it up out
there in the field. Now that's probably why the גמרא *Gemara* says
that at least rabbinically, מכר *mecher* is קובע *koveya*. Right? So that's
what happens. And so if you sold it, that's קובע *koveya*. Because
that's... so when you have the stuff out in the field, you're
going to do one of two things. Either you're going to bring
it home and eat it, or you're going to sell it. So
that exactly just strikes me right now, that's conceptually the reason that
מכר *mecher* is קובע *koveya*. In the bringing home scenario, you're חייב
*chayav* when you bring it home, and in the selling scenario, it
never gets home, it stays out in the field, you're חייב *chayav*
when you sell it. Yeah, but it was relation before the original
owner. That was just a side point about whether whether biblically when
somebody purchases it, they're חייב *chayav* or not. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says biblically they're not and then we had a whole discussion about
it matters when they purchase it, okay? But rabbinically you are when
you buy it regardless. A purchaser is always חייב *chayav*. And not
only that, the מכר *mecher* is a קובע *koveya*, you know, is
that other step after the גמר מלאכה *gmar melacha*. Yeah. Grapes you
can pick right off the vine and eat them, but olives need
to be soaked in salt water to become edible. So I don't
know what to say about it then because the גמרא seems to
say that there isn't a process. Yeah, maybe it really just means
grapes, but that's a good point. Alright, we're moving on, חברה, chevre,
we're moving on. Okay, so now we finally, thankfully, we get back
to workers. So the גמרא says like this: אשכחן אדם במחובר ושור
בתלוש. Ashkachan adam bemachubar veshor betolush. We know in the פסוקים pesukim
that a person can eat when he's dealing with stuff that's growing
as he's harvesting it at the time of גמר מלאכה, and an
ox deals with can eat, you know, you can't muzzle it when
it's dealing with stuff that's been harvested, when it's threshing, and that's
שלא בשעת גמר מלאכה. shelo besha'as gemar melacha. The stuff in the
post-harvesting process is not done with the processing. אדם בתלוש מנלן? Adam
betolush minalan? How do you know a man has a right to
eat, a worker has a right to eat when he is dealing
with the stuff after it's been harvested? So the גמרא says like
this, right? Yeah, קל וחומר משור, kal vachomer mishor, you learn it
out from a שור, shor, an ox. ומה שור שאין אוכל במחובר
אוכל בתלוש, Umah shor she'ein ochel bemachubar ochel betolush, an ox who
cannot eat when stuff is attached, the Torah only says you allow
an ox to eat when it's actually been harvested already and he's,
you know, it's being he's threshing it. אדם שאוכל במחובר, Adam she'ochel
bemachubar, so a person who has the right to eat when he's
working on it when it's attached, אינו דין שיאכל בתלוש? eino din
she'yochal betolush? He should certainly be no worse than an ox. He
has a right that the ox doesn't have, so he should certainly
have the same right that the ox has to eat it when
it's תלוש. tolush. Of course, you could just say maybe they're mutually
exclusive. Alright, whatever, that's your classic קל וחומר kal vachomer which we
always have a problem with. Anyway, the גמרא says no, מה לשור
שכן אתה מצווה חסימתו תאמר באדם שאי אתה מצווה חסימתו? mah leshor
sheken atah metzuveh chasimaso tomar be'adam she'ein atah metzuveh chasimaso? No, no,
no, an ox were more strict or he has more right if
you want to put it that way because as we just said
earlier, even if a worker has rights when he's dealing with grain
after it's been harvested, you don't transgress a biblical prohibition if you
muzzle your worker. You only transgress a biblical prohibition if you muzzle
your ox. So since we know that even להלכה lehalacha an ox,
you know, has this greater demand that you transgress if you muzzle
your ox, maybe the הלכה halacha that an ox can eat, you
know, is limited to an ox as well, maybe a worker doesn't
have the right to eat in that case. Animal rights סוגיא. Exactly.
So the גמרא says okay, מכל וחומר משור, mikal vachomer mishor, so
the גמרא says יהא אדם, yehei adam, so now the גמרא says
okay, let's challenge that, ויהא אדם מצווה חסימתו מכל וחומר משור. veyehei
adam metzuveh chasimaso mikal vachomer mishor. ומה שור שאין אתה מצווה להחיותו,
Umah shor she'ein atah metzuveh le'hachayoso, here's here you get it, right?
This is really fascinating from an animal rights perspective. You don't have
an obligation to sustain the life of an animal. You're allowed to
even kill them, right, for meat? Okay, nevertheless, אתה מצווה חסימתו, atah
metzuveh chasimaso, you're not allowed to muzzle them. It's really interesting. It's
the difference between צער בעלי חיים tzar ba'alei chayim and killing animals.
The גמרא has no problem with killing animals, right, you know, they're
there whatever they can serve human needs, etc. It has a problem
with inflicting pain on animals. Okay, so you're not commanded to keep
it alive but but you can't muzzle. אדם שאתה מצווה להחיותו, Adam
she'atah metzuveh le'hachayoso, human beings that you're commanded to keep them alive,
אינו דין שאתה מצווה חסימתו, eino din she'atah metzuveh chasimaso, much more
so should you not be allowed to muzzle humans and you would
transgress? אמר קרא, Amar kra, now we get the פסוק we were
quoting before, כנפשך, kenafshecha, כנפשו של פועל, kenafsho shel po'el, מה נפשו
אם חסמו פטור, mah nafsho im chasamo patur, like you is the
worker, the same way yourself if you muzzle yourself you're exempt, אף
פועל אם חסמו פטור, af po'el im chasamo patur, the worker as
well. So no, we know you're exempt for a worker from muzzling.
You don't transgress. Okay, so now we're back to where we were.
ואלא אדם בתלוש מנלן? Ve'ela adam betolush minallan? So okay, if only
an ox you transgress when you muzzle him, maybe only an ox
has a right to eat the grain if תלוש, tolush, maybe a
human being that's dealing with stuff that's harvested doesn't have a right
to eat. אמר קרא, Amar kra, גמר מלאכה. אמר קרא, Amar kra,
קמה קמה בי זמני. kama kama bei zimni. It says, you know,
כי תבא בקמת רעך ki tavo bekamat re'echa and there's another וחרמש
תניף על קמת רעך. vehermesh tinif al kamat re'echa. It says the
word קמה kama twice. אין ענין לאדם במחובר, ein inyan le'adam bemachubar,
you don't need that word to tell me you have a right
when you're doing it when you're dealing with stuff that's growing because
that's what the פסוק is talking about. So what is the extra
word קמה kama coming to tell me? תניהו ענין לאדם בתלוש, tineihu
inyan le'adam betolush, to tell me that there's another place human beings
have a right to eat, not just the stuff that's growing but
even when they deal with stuff that's been harvested. So that's one
place we learn it out from, not from the ox but from
the double language of קמה קמה. kama kama. Maybe the ox gave
us the idea, but we learn it out from the doubling of
the word. ואמאי הדר אדם בתלוש לא צריך קרא. Ve'amai hadar adam
betolush lo tzarich kra. You don't need a פסוק to tell me
a human being can eat stuff when he's working on it stuff
that's been harvested. כתיב, כי תבא בכרם רעך, ki tavo bekerem re'echa,
when you come into your friend's vineyard. מי לא עסקינן ששכרו לקטף?
mi lo askinan she'secharo likatef? The Torah doesn't tell you how you're
hiring him. Who says you're hiring him to pick? Maybe you're hiring
him, he's going into your vineyard to shlep the grapes. Okay, so
since the Torah doesn't specify, it includes both the guy who's picking
the grapes and the guy who's shlepping the grapes. ואמר רחמנא ואכל,
ve'amar rachmana ve'achal, and the Torah says you can eat. So that's
how we know that a human being can eat even if it's
already been harvested. Well, you'd eat a bunch. I mean, you'd— Well,
right, you don't need a דרשה. drasha. As he's sort of saying,
it's implicit in the פשט. You're right. Anyway, let's just read one
more line which is the flip: שור במחובר מנא ליה. Shor b'mechubar
minaleh. Now, the whole point we were saying before is that a
person is better than an ox that a person eats במחובר b'mechubar
and an ox doesn't. But now we're actually going to say, that's
just what the פסוקים psukim sounded like. The actual הלכה halacha is
that if an ox is working by harvesting grapes, you know, when
the stuff is connected, is growing, the ox also is allowed to
eat. Okay? So how do you know that? קל וחומר מאדם. Kal
v'chomer m'adam. Now let's make it a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. מה
אדם שאינו אוכל בתלוש, Mah adam she'eino ochel b'talush, a person can't
eat when it's harvested, which isn't true, but—you can't do this. What?
You can't do this? I know, I know. Don't get caught up.
Let's just get through. Anyway, not only that, we're making a קל
וחומר kal v'chomer from something that's false. It's just the גמרא saying
the פשט of the פסוקים. psukim. The פסוקים psukim don't say that
a human can eat בתלוש. b'talush. The הלכה is that a human
can eat בתלוש. b'talush. But I just go with it. We're already
overtime. So it's the same. A person that the פסוקים psukim don't
explicitly tell him he can eat בתלוש, b'talush, אוכל במחובר, ochel b'mechubar,
he can eat במחובר. b'mechubar. שור שאוכל בתלוש, Shor she'ochel b'talush, an
ox that eats when it's תלוש, talush, אינו דין שיאכל במחובר? eino
din she'yochal b'mechubar? Certainly it should eat. Of course, we can have
a million problems with that. But anyway, no. מה אדם שכן אתה
מצווה להחיותו? Mah adam she'kein atah m'tzuvah l'hachayoto? Maybe human beings eat
במחובר b'mechubar because you have a great obligation to keep them alive.
תאמר בשור שאי אתה מצווה להחיותו? Tomer b'shor she'ee atah m'tzuvah l'hachayoto?
It's not by ox. So maybe oxen don't have that right. So
the גמרא says, okay, maybe you should have that obligation by oxen.
ויש אתה מצווה להחיותו מקל וחומר. V'yesh atah m'tzuvah l'hachayoto m'kal v'chomer.
Let's say you have that obligation to oxen to keep them alive.
ומה אדם שאי אתה מצווה על חסימתו, U'mah adam she'ee atah m'tzuvah
al chasimato, a human being you're not prohibited to muzzle, אתה מצווה
להחיותו, atah m'tzuvah l'hachayoto, you have to keep him alive. שור שאתה
מצווה על חסימתו, Shor she'atah m'tzuvah al chasimato, an ox that you're
not allowed to muzzle, אינו דין שאתה מצווה להחיותו? eino din she'atah
m'tzuvah l'hachayoto? You should certainly keep them alive. So all the vegans
in the room are very happy because here the גמרא has a
הוה אמינא that you would never be able to slaughter oxen. I
don't know what you do with all the פסוקים psukim in the
תורה that say you eat meat. But anyway, אמר קרא וחי אחיך
עמך, Amar kra v'chei achicha imach, אחיך ולא שור. achicha v'lo shor.
You only have an obligation towards a fellow human being, not an
ox. Okay, so now we're back to our question. Last line. ואלא
לשור במחובר מנלן? V'ela l'shor b'mechubar minalan? So how do you know
that an ox can eat במחובר? b'mechubar? Sorry. So how do you
know that an ox can eat במחובר b'mechubar if you can't learn
it from a human because a human you have a מצווה להחיותו?
mitzvah l'hachayoto? אמר קרא ריעך ריעך ב' פעמים. Amar kra re'acha re'acha
beis pe'amim. It says כמה ריעך. kama re'acha. אם אינו עניין לאדם
במחובר? Im eino inyan l'adam b'mechubar? That's another doubling. So we don't
have to tell me that a human can eat במחובר, b'mechubar, that's
explicit. We don't have to tell me a human can eat בתלוש,
b'talush, that we learned out from קמא. So what do we do
with this extra doubling? תנהו עניין לשור במחובר Tneh inyan l'shor b'mechubar
to tell you that an ox can also eat just like a
human במחובר, b'mechubar, an ox can also eat by במחובר. b'mechubar. All
right, anyway, to be continued tomorrow.